more than ever there's this revolution
in non-ordinary states of consciousness
and that people are using them to mend
trauma they are using them to access
information and inspiration and they're
using them to connect and collaborate in
ways that haven't necessarily been
possible at this scale before that's all
good news and that's creating a ton of
positive things both in personal growth
and development adjuncts to different
psycho therapies and medical
interventions increases in solving hard
problems that we face as entrepreneurs
or as a society so we're talking about
like micro dosing we're talking about
all sorts of different experiment you
could really I mean and certainly the
premise that Stephen Connor and I wrote
about in stealing fire is that it's the
neuro chemistry we have access to you
know that's our toolkit and you can get
to it through a bunch of different means
you can use smart tech you can use
meditation you can use breathing
techniques and use sexuality you can use
pharmacology you can use dance and
movement and music really that to me is
the interest the most interesting thing
of all it's not what's the flavor of the
week and what does a new study tell us
it's that we understand the
neurophysiology of human optimization
and transcendence now now the
interesting thing is no sooner do you
have that experience of being able to
prompt ecstatic or moments where we step
beyond ourselves and you could call flow
States there's a there's a lot of
different Peake states that would fall
under that big tent and you end up with
you know people bonding very closely
with the folks they share those
experiences with what Victor Turner the
anthropologist would recall communitas
so the moment you have ecstatically
inspired community then you have to kind
of just tackle head-on the question and
the liability of the cult because a cult
and you know most of us when we think of
that we think of it in the sort of
scandalous terms we think of it in the
helter skelter Manson family or the Jim
Jones drink the kool-aid side but from
you know religious studies or
anthropology a cult is literally just a
community of practice bonded together
around some
Eppie fanuc you know or revelatory
experience basically it's any religious
group that doesn't yet that is not yet
state sanctioned is a cult so the
question is is we know there are
dysfunctional ones we know there are
lots and lots of unethical cults
particularly where leaders hijack money
power sexuality and control and even
pick pick any two and you're done you
know so the question is is rather than
steering away from that and as and
saying that won't happen or it shouldn't
happen or that's not what we're doing
steer into it and say okay if we're
gonna build vibrant communities of
practice how do we build ethical cults
and and what I would imagine and that's
clearly a conversation for us all to
figure out but what I would imagine is
that you know we've seen this movie
before we know how this goes badly wrong
and we've had about a half century of
you know Eastern hierarchical lineage
traditions getting buggered up and
bastardized and imported into the West
and varying kind of gurus with feet of
clay stepping up to lead Children's
Crusade you know that all just go off
the cliff and so the question would be
if we're trying to build ethical cults
VA you know are they experimental and
experiential so that there is no Dogma
or doctrine to buy into they
decentralized so that people maintain
their own common sense their own
judgment and their own agency and and
are they pointed towards I would hope
some sort of social good or action and
and can you and and all of the the known
issues of dysfunctional cult can we just
say hey let's just forever be vigilant
about shared in groups about specific
vernacular about an inside-outside group
mentality about mediated access to
ecstasy right and that's another kicker
cuz they're almost in every single one
of those situations where it does go
wrong that group does something together
that creates a state experience that
they come to believe is exceptional
special and quite often is doled out or
tightly controlled by the person in
charge and so if we create distributed
access to techniques of ecstasy so
everybody is on their own recognizance
you know and responsible for
having access to these things
integrating them and growing them there
are no fish stories to swallow so it's
it's open source meaning making and
there's no sage on the stage there's
nobody up front there has lopsided truth
or authority claims that maybe we have
the chance and then also you know a
great one from a lot of religious
traditions that seems to get skipped
these days is an ethic of service are we
doing something with this or are we just
gonna crawling up our arses and engaging
in endless self-development so that
would be my hope is that is that ethical
code building is the game of how do we
create lots of nodes all of which are
unique and different from each other
they all form with their own kind of
local DNA and particular missions and
purposes they may even have their own
belief systems but we can say X tosses
the peak experience catharsis the
healing and communitas become the kind
of three-legged stool that you can
basically build tightly net highly
collaborative functional and effective
small communities around what's the
benefit of creating these kind of flow
States in the first place well I think I
mean the benefits of many and much of
the research you know starting in
University of Chicago going through lots
of other organizations and universities
has just been that flow states tend to
create a lot of positive benefits
including heightened and more precise
decision-making a lot of sort of rather
than meditation and stillness it's sort
of meditation in action so you have
real-time decision-making you have
increased problem-solving increased
innovation increased connectivity in
group flow situations or like heightened
team situations and then you also tend
to have a high self-reported spike in
overall life satisfaction so on a
simplest sense I guess I kind of think
about those peak States almost like when
your laptop has been left open too long
and you've got too many browser windows
open it starts bogging down and getting
glitchy and that's kind of how we are
these days so that continuous partial
attention there's never a time where we
truly decompress even on planes now how
do those Wi-Fi follows us everywhere our
smartphones follow us everywhere the
natural rhythms of life have all just
been ironed out even in you know urinals
and gas stations we're getting bombed by
laughs there's just no down time so most
of us are suffering from some version of
sort of almost micro PTSD constantly our
nervous systems are just fibrillating
and so cultivating these peak states is
like just doing a cold reset on your
laptop it just lets our nervous systems
power down and then when we come back
online we come back to a neutral balance
spot and from there we have choice and
it may not last for a long time we may
get overwhelmed with the wind with the
barrage again but at least we have that
bit of space to return to Center and
start living from there again and the
more regularly we can do that then that
becomes that becomes a known location
and we can kind of use it to find
ourselves again and with the onslaught
of you know all the information these
none ordinary states are these what's
tangrowth for example was talking about
yeah absolutely and and non-ordinary
states literally can mean anything other
than waking state consciousness in
stealing fire and in general in the kind
of optimal psychology space we tend to
skew to the ones I mean schizophrenia
would be a non-ordinary states will be a
non-ordinary state manias would be
non-ordinary states as well but i think
stan grof and and that the rest of that
sort of broad discipline would generally
described them as optimal and helpful
states that don't correlate with normal
waking consciousness which is typically
first beta wave your electric activity
prefrontal cortical executive functional
activity and often as we said some form
of a mild vigilance or arousal stress
response